Finding Aid for the S.A. Griffin collection of underground poetry, Scott Wannberg, and The Carma Bums LSC.2248
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Writings collected by Griffin (Box 23, Box 24, Box 25, Box 26, Box 27, Box 28, Box 29, Box 30, Box 31, Box 32, Box 33, Box 34, Box 35, Box 36, Box 37, Box 38, Box 39, Box 40, Box 41, Box 42, Box 43, Box 44, Box 45, Box 46, Box 47, Box 48, Box 49, Box 50, Box 51, Box 52, Box 53, Box 54, Box 55, Box
  - Subject files, 1973-2014 (Box 162, Box 163, Box 164, Box 165, Box 166, Box 167, Box 168)
    - Bukowski, Charles (Box 168, Folder 1, Box 162, Folder 9-14, Box 163, Folder 1-6)
      Box 162: Everything Bukowski including broadsides about Buk, birthday remembrances, postcards, stickers, Celebrating Bukowski at The Huntington program signed by Neeli Cherkovski, signed poems, signed photographs, signed Paget Press catalogues, Black Sparrow Press catalogues, Jeffrey H. Weinberg Books catalogues, and Under the Influence catalogue with photographs by Michael Montfort.
      Box 163: More Bukowski materials including Postal Worker USPS stamps, Black Sparrow Press postcards, bookmarks, birthday cards, posters, clippings, photographs by Michael Montfort, and clippings.
      Box 168: Black Sparrow press publicity materials including Charles Bukowski matchbooks.
      According to Griffin, Charles Bukowski was an early, important, and lasting influence on his work and a one-man revolution in post- World War II poetry. Not to be confused with Beat era writers, Bukowski is considered the Godfather of what might be "meat" or "confessional" poetics.
    - Bukowski, Linda, 1996, 2003, 2009 (Box 163, Folder 7-8)
      Linda's color photographs of Griffin and Perrotta, a poem for Lorraine by Linda, President Linda Lee Bukowski's The Charles Bukowski Foundation stationary, and Owner Linda L. Beighle's Dewdrop Inn business card.
      Linda Bukowski is Charles Bukowski's widow who oversees his literary estate. Linda was a friend of Griffin and his wife Lorraine Perrotta, 1994-2011.
    - Burroughs, William S., 1993, 1998 (Box 163, Folder 9)
      Christopher Felver Beat postcard, UCLA Library select bibiliography, Giorno Poetry Systems catalogue, and Ports of Entry: William S. Burroughs and the Arts LACMA mailer.
      According to Griffin, William S. Burroughs is a cut & paste, original issue Beat writer, innovator, and dream machine prophet of punk who is a big influence.
    - The Carma Bums, 1990, 1994, 1995 (Box 163, Folder 10)
      Mike M. Mollett's "Brief & Non-Expurgated Preliminary History of The Carma Bums", Why We Need To Have A Meeting (Meetings), and "We Firemen Spray Gasoline" typescript for The Carma Bums Tour of Words 1990.
      Performance poetry group created by S.A. Griffin in the summer of 1989 after a trip to Denver where he was on location as a guest star for a Perry Mason movie of the week Case of The All Star Assassin. The Carma Bums were conceived to only exist on the road as part poetry, performance, Dada and a lot improv / happening. The original group was Michael Lane Bruner, S.A. Griffin, Doug Knott, Bobbo Staron, and Scott Wannberg. They invited Laurel Ann Bogen to be part of the original group, but according to Griffin she declined, saying that she'd "done her time sleeping on floors." They brought on Ellyn Maybe to open for them. Mike M. Mollett joined the group in 1990. Bobbo Staron dropped out after 1992. The Carma Bums toured the U.S. and Canada, 1989-2009. In 1994 they travelled to the University of Washington, Seattle for a week to create The Carma Bums International Superhighway Tour of Words. The Carma Bums mostly toured in Griffin's 1959 Cadillac Farther. The group disbanded after Scott Wannberg's death on August 19, 2011. The Carma Bums are the subject of the documentary The Luxurious Tigers of Obnoxious Agreement.
    - Cohen, Leonard, 2009 (Box 163, Folder 11)
      "Leonard Cohen: One of Those Guys" Sore Dove Press Release postcard for Robert Humphrey's tribute to Cohen's history as a poet, novelist, songwriter, and Zen Buddhist.
      According to Griffin, Leonard Cohen was a powerful poetic influence about the same time that Griffin began to read Charles Bukowski, Jack Kerouac, and the Beats. Earlier influences would include Carl Sandburg, Edgar Allan Poe, William Ernest Henley, Elizabeth Barrett Browning, Rod McKuen, and Rudyard Kipling.
    - Coleman, Wanda, 2005, 2013 (Box 163, Folder 12-13)
      Poetry Society of America program which honors Coleman, Lhasa Club reading flyer, interviews, and memorial compilation which includes clippings and "She" poem for Coleman by Austin Straus.
      Wanda Coleman was a friend and early supporter of Griffin's work as both a poet and a performer. Coleman named Griffin the Best Performance Poet for The LA Weekly in 1989. An influence and mentor to countless young poets and writers, Coleman was mentored by John Thomas and close to Philomene Long at her death.
    - Corso, Gregory, 1959, 2001 (Box 163, Folder 14)
      Corso's 2001 Time Magazine obituary and a clipping from a 1959 Time Magazine which features a photograph of "Beatniks" Corso, Ginsberg and Orlovsky.
      According to Griffin, Gregory Corso was a big poetic influence and quite possibly his favorite of the Beat poets. Griffin considers his Corso's poem "Bomb" one of the most important poems of the 20th Century.
    - Crews, Harry (Box 163, Folder 15)
      Short film script by R. Bruce Dickson based on the novel Car by Harry Crews.
      Harry Crews was a Southern writer and literary influence on Griffin. Griffin never met him but got to know him through his friend Bruce Dickson who was working with Crews on a screen adaptation of Crews's story Car at his death.
    - Dada (Box 163, Folder 16)
      Articles on Dada and Futurism, postcards, and a piece on The Variety Theatre which includes a phone list of members.
      According to Griffin, "Dada is what makes the art wheels and process spin." Griffin was brought into the mail art network and introduced to Dada ideas by Mike M. Mollett.
    - Death Row Last Meal Requests (Box 163, Folder 17)
      Last meal requests for Gary Gilmore and other prisoners who were executed.
      This human account of what death row inmates request for their last meals was given to Griffin by Peter Lownds.
    - Drehmer, Aleathia, 2007 (Box 163, Folder 18)
      Postcards, a brochure, and business cards for the co-editor of Zygote in My Coffee.
      Aleathia Drehmer edited and published Durable Goods, a small, handmade poetry broadside / handout.
    - Dutton, Doug, 2008 March 30 (Box 163, Folder 19)
      Text of Doug Dutton's remarks at Dutton's Brentwood Books' closing party.
      Doug Dutton owned Dutton's Books in Brentwood where Scott Wannberg worked. According to Griffin, Dutton was an avid supporter of small press and big personal support for Wannberg.
    - Exit, Deborah (Box 163, Folder 20)
      Reviews and Lhasa Club gig flyers and for "poet rocker" Deborah Exit.
      Deborah Exit (Deborah Sweet) was a poet, performance artist, and producer who ran X=Art during the 1980s in West Hollywood. X=Art was a floating performance venue featuring musicians, artists, performance artists, and poets all on the same show. Today Dr. Deborah Sweet is a practicing therapist.
    - francEyE, 2008 (Box 163, Folder 21)
      Flyer for publication of Grandma Stories and color copy of Diana Bonebrake's painting The Joy Theatre, New Orleans 2006 which was used for the cover of FrancEyE's Call published by Rose of Sharon Press.
      francEyE was a poet, supporter of poets and poetry, and friend of Griffin's. She is the mother of Marina Bukowski, Charles Bukowski's only child. Griffin edited and published her book Call, the last book to be published for her while she was alive and the only book published during her life to have color covers and be perfect bound.
    - Gehman, Pleasant, undated (Box 163, Folder 22)
      A White Trash Apocalypse photograph and book reviews, clippings, and flyers for Burlesk a Go-Go, Honk if yer Horny, The Ringling Sisters, and The Underground Guide To Los Angeles.
      Pleasant Gehman is a poet, writer, journalist, performance artist, belly dancer, actress, singer, L.A. punk progenitor, and friend of Griffin's. Gehman was one of the original Go-Gos and a member of the Screaming Sirens, Ringling Sisters, and Honk if Yr Horny. Gehman created White Trash Apocalypse in 1995 with Iris Berry and S.A. Griffin.
    - Ginsberg, Allen, 1997, circa 2010 (Box 163, Folder 23)
      Allen Ginsberg's America commemorative program, a color copy of a Ginsberg photograph, and publicity materials for Howl.
      Allen Ginsberg was a Beat poet 20th century icon. In the late 1980s Griffin asked Ginsberg what he thought poetry might be. After about three hours of discussion while waiting for his plane at LAX the conclusion was: candor. Griffin believes, "Ginsberg changed the world with his public reading of Howl, its subsequent publication and landmark trial. There is no Beat movement without him."
    - The Grassy Knoll (Box 163, Folder 24)
      A reading flyer and call for journal submissions and a copy of The Grassy Knoll's quarterly journal onTarget, edited by Anderson Stone.
      The Grassy Knoll was a thrift store, coffee shop, and performance venue located on Sunset Boulevard in Silver Lake during the 1990s. Griffin read and performed poetry downstairs in the basement, primarily in conjunction with Anderson Stone's poetry serial On Target.
    - Griffin, Spencer (Box 163, Folder 25)
      Poems, artwork, scholastic writing assignments, and various school assignments by Griffin's son.
      Spencer Griffin is Griffin's only child by his second wife, Sharon Grish Griffin. Spencer was born in Santa Monica, California on December 29, 1987 and diagnosed as autistic by Dr. BJ Freeman (UCLA) in 1990. Griffin's brother and sister Robin and Robert were diagnosed as "mentally retarded" when they were about 1-2 years old, and it was later suggested that they were more than likely misdiagnosed at the time, both of them quite possibly on the autism spectrum. When Dr. Freeman explained to the Griffins why she considered Spencer to be autistic, Griffin believed he too must be autistic. Sharon and S.A. have since concluded that Spencer has Asperger's. Griffin is deeply proud of his son, who graduated from Village Glen High School in Sherman Oaks, attended Glendale Community College and Pasadena City College, and received his AA from American River College. Spencer received his BA from UC Davis in 2015 with a major in linguistics. He plays guitar and writes music and poetry. Griffin published When Is The Future? (Rose of Sharon, 1997) for him when he was ten years old.
    - Herms, George, 1965 (Box 164, Folder 1)
      A Spring Visions exhibition Stryke Gallery flyer and color copies of collages.
      George Herms was an assemblage artist, performance artist, and poet.
    - H.I.P., 2009 (Box 164, Folder 2)
      A Hollywood Institute of Poetics (H.I.P.) events calendar.
      The Hollywood Institute of Poetics was created by S.A. Griffin and Rafael FJ Alvarado. The acronym was originally meant as a joke on "hip" culture. Individuals from H.I.P. were honored by the city of Los Angeles for their work within the community.
    - Hoffberg, Judith Ann, 2009 (Box 164, Folder 3)
      Memorial program; memorial stamp set by Creative Thing; and a color photograph of Mike M. Mollett, Griffin, Hoffberg, and "CT" Caldera, "with a little bit of Lon Spiegelman."
      Judith Hoffberg was a librarian, mail artist and friend to Griffin. Hoffberg co-founded ARLIS and supported a global community of mail artists.
    - Holy Fools Week (Box 164, Folder 4-5)
      Correspondence, notes, address list, and Los Angeles County Registrar Fictitious Business Name Statements.
      A failed attempt at creating a week-long Beat happening in Wichita, Kansas, 1999-2000. Griffin partnered with San Francisco poet and performance artist James Stauffer after the two met on the BEAT-L listserv in the mid 1990s, which was created by Bill Gargan out of SUNY New York. Holy Fools Week was centered around Charles Plymell, one of the major voices on the Beat-L and one of the Vortex Beats, which included Bob Branaman, Bruce Conner, Stan Brakhage and Dave Haselwood. Griffin and Stauffer worked on the project daily for a year and published two issues of The Fool, a magazine created to promote and reflect the event, but ultimately they could not raise the capital to fund the event.
    - Homeless Writers Coalition, 1990, 1994, 2000, 2001 (Box 164, Folder 6-7)
      Poetry, clippings, event flyers, Homeless Writers Forum publication, articles, and a copy of The Word issue #1.
      This coalition was established in the 1990s as a creative collective of Los Angeles homeless poets, writers and filmmakers to address the homeless in America by promoting the creative community among the homeless. Griffin was brought onto the board by poet Robert Chambers.
    - Howard, Justice, undated (Box 164, Folder 8)
      A handwritten poem by Howard; a flyer for an exhibition of her photography; and a copy of Outlaw, a profile on Howard by John Gilmore.
      Justice Howard is a poet, writer and photographer. Howard and Griffin co-authored Without Skin (1989), a rare chapbook that includes photos and poetry with a cover by Justice Howard.
    - Iguana Cafe, 1989, 1993 (Box 164, Folder 9)
      Event calendars.
      The Iguana Café was a major gathering place in North Hollywood for musicians, poets and the off-beat from the late 1980s until its closing in 1995. It was owned and operated by Tom Ianello at 10943 Camarillo Street where The Carma Bums began their 1990 No Seat Belts Tour of Words. Regular performers included Tracy Theilen, Dan Bern, and Matthew Mars. Poets that met and performed there regularly included Erica Erdman, Amelie Frank, Carlye Archibeque, Allen J. Freedman (one of the Water Espresso Gallery regulars), and Uncle Don Fanning.
    - Kaufman, Bob (Box 164, Folder 10)
      One color "Bagel Shop Jazz" calendar page.
      Bob Kaufman is a legendary San Francisco Beat poet. Kaufman was friends with San Francisco poets Jack Micheline and A.D. Winans and influenced their work.
    - Kenney, Shawna, 2000 (Box 164, Folder 11)
      Clippings and a press release for I Was A Teenage Dominatrix.
      Shawna Kenney is a writer, journalist, and author of I Was A Teenage Dominatrix. A friend of Griffin's, he officiated her marriage to Rich Dollinger in Malibu, close to where the last scene from the original Planet of The Apes was shot. Kenney is a vegan activist presently writing for Vice.
    - Kerouac, Jack (Box 164, Folder 12)
      Excerpts from On The Road scroll typescript, flyer, postcard, program, and article about the original manuscript.
      Jack Kerouac is a legendary Beat writer and poet who influenced Griffin's writing and thinking. Griffin considers On The Road one of the most important books he has read.
    - Kerouac, Jan, 1989, undated (Box 164, Folder 13)
      Obituary clippings; obituary memo by Doug Knott; and photocopies of her correspondence, photos and recipes.
      Jack Kerouac's daughter and only child, Jan Kerouac was a writer who authored Trainsong, Baby Driver, and Parrot Fever. Griffin was supposed to be on a panel with her at the Bancroft Library in 1995, but she was too ill to attend and died soon after in 1996.
    - Kesey, Ken, 2006 (Box 164, Folder 14)
      Clipping concerning the restoration of Kesey's 1939 International bus dubbed Further.
      Ken Kesey was a writer, performance artist, and progenitor of the Merry Pranksters who influenced Griffin as a writer, thinker, and performance artist.
    - Knott, Doug (Box 164, Folder 15-18)
      Clippings; poetry articles; color photographs of Griffin and Perrotta; bios for The Carma Bums; and writings by Knott, Mike M. Mollett, and The Carma Bums.
      Doug Knott is Griffin's friend and performance partner who was born and raised in Florida and relocated to San Francisco and Marin before permanently moving to Los Angeles in the early 1980s. Knott is a lawyer, poet, writer, performance artist, and actor who performed with the following: The Lost Tribe, Wounded Theatre, Dead Beats, The Carma Bums, and Lost Bums. Griffin met Knott at The Water Espresso Gallery in the early 1980s. Knott created a long running series of punk variety shows for The Lhasa Club in the 1980s, and in the 1990s he co-founded the Famous-Knott Salon with Cheri Famous.
    - Krech, Richard (Box 164, Folder 19)
      Poetry by Krech and a "My Other Vehicle Is The Mahayana" bumper sticker.
      Richard Krech of Berkeley, California is a criminal defense lawyer, poet, and activist. Griffin published and edited 3 by Richard Krech (Rose of Sharon, 2008), a folded broadside.
    - The L.A. Mudpeople (Box 164, Folder 20-22)
      Photographs, flyers, and clippings.
      This performance group founded by Mike M. Mollett in 1988.Originally called The Mudmen, they later changed their name to The L.A. Mudmen, and today they exist as The L.A. Mudpeople. These urban nomads describe themselves as "primal, curious and innocent but not stupid. Non-verbal and often silent. Slow-moving and deliberate, discovering wonderful moments in the places most people by-pass, overlook or step thru [sic]. Mudpeople are liberated without the concept of time, hurry and stress. Mudpeople live in contrast to a frenetic world." Over the years, the group's membership has included aerobics instructors, artists, actors, publishers, gardeners, teachers, access cable hosts, George and Peggy DiCaprio, and Griffin's wife, librarian Lorraine Perrotta, who has been a member of the Mudpeople for over 20 years.
    - Lennon, John (Box 164, Folder 23)
      A copy of "A Love Letter From John and Yoko To People Who Ask Us What, When, And Why" and a transcript of a three-hour interview conducted with John and Yoko Ono Lennon at the request of the RKO Radio Network.
      Griffin considers John Lennon a working class hero.
    - levy, d.a. (Box 164, Folder 24, Box 168, Folder 2)
      Box 164: Rabbits Over Clevyland coasters printed by Bill Roberts of Bottle of Smoke Press, rabbit drawing by Tom Kryss, "a belated touche for d.a. levy" by Kent Taylor, photocopy of The Buddhist Third Class Junkmail Oracle, and d.a. levy birthday bash flyer.
      Box 168: Two copies of Speaking for the dumb which includes poems by levy and a piece by Griffin on publishing via his small press imprint, Rose of Sharon Press.
      Mimeo revolutionary d.a. levy from Cleveland, Ohio influenced Griffin's thinking, publishing, and writing. With Bree Bodnar of Cleveland, Griffin co-produced Rabbits Over Clevyland in 2006 as tribute to not only levy, but levy's mimeo revolution cohort and friend, poet and artist Tom Kryss. Griffin produced an on the spot mimeo book collectively written by the poet attendees of the event in the basement of Mac's Backs Books in Cleveland using publisher Bill Roberts's mimeo machine. The cover features an original silk-screened rabbit created by Tom Kryss for the books and the images were screened in Jake and Cindy Marx's front room in Cleveland. The rabbit is Kryss's signature image, a symbol of "rabbits everywhere" reflecting levy's ethic to "cover the city (of Cleveland) with lines (of poetry)" in service of this cultural revolution.
    - The Lhasa Club, 1987 (Box 164, Folder 25)
      An article on the closure of the Lhasa Club
      The Lhasa Club (1982-1988) was a Hollywood punk / performance venue owned and operated by Jean-Pierre Boccara and his partner Anna Mariani. Griffin produced a number of events there and was a regular reader and performer at the club which was connected to The Water Espresso Gallery via a common hallway. Griffin considers The Water and The Lhasa as a home for The Lost Tribe.
    - Locklin, Gerald, undated, 1998-2002, 2009 (Box 164, Folder 26)
      Black and white photographs of Locklin, correspondence, and poems.
      Gerald Locklin is a poet, writer, and a former Long Beach State professor who served as the poetry editor for Chiron Review since 1989.
    - Long, Philomene (Box 164, Folder 27)
      Poetry reading flyers, memorial cards, Beyond Baroque Memorial Tribute program, holiday cards from Long and John Thomas, photographs of Long and Thomas, "Smaller Than A Breadbox" by Thomas, poetry by Long and a copy of the Beachhead with headline, "Venice Loses Its Poet Laureate -- Philomene Long, RIP."
      Philomene Long was a Venice West poet and filmmaker; Poet Laureate of Venice, California; The Queen of Bohemia; Stuart Z. Perkoff's last lover; and John Thomas's wife and widow. Griffin describes his friend as an escapee from the nunnery, who lived her life dedicated to the poem.
    - Micheline, Jack (Box 165, Folder 1-4)
      One CD.
      Poems, drawings, paintings, photographs, watercolors, performance flyers, clippings, Jack Micheline in Amsterdam CD, J ack Micheline: Poet Of The People typescript by A.D. Winans, and This Cat Eats Everything postcards.
      Jack Micheline was a poet and artist who was part of the San Francisco Beat Renaissance. His first book, River of Red Wine (1958), contains a forward written by Jack Kerouac. Griffin met Micheline through his association with The Moment and ended up producing some of his last shows in Los Angeles. The Outlaw Bible of American Poetry happened because of Micheline's passing. A Beat poet and street poet, Micheline is also considered an "outlaw" poet. Micheline was a friend of A.D. Winans and Bob Kaufman. After Micheline's death, Winans worked with the city of San Francisco to name a street after Micheline. Give America A Break: A Tribute To Jack Micheline, a two LP set produced by San Francisco's Unrequited Records (2014) includes a track by Griffin.
    - Mollett, Mike M. (Box 165, Folder 5)
      Michael Mollett matchbook, The Wedding Ceremony of Dee Balson and Michael Mollett program, ZTZU flyer, poems and S.A. Griffin's Nuthing Sacred interview with Mollett and Lorraine Perrotta of the L.A. Mudpeople, and "After the Break In" by Mollett and Michael Bruner.
      Mollett is a poet, mail artist, Dadaist, performance artist, and Griffin's friend and performance partner. Founder of The L.A. Mudpeople, Mike M. Mollett was a member of The Lost Tribe, The Carma Bums and The Lost Bums. Mollett brought Griffin into the worlds of Dada, Fluxism and mail art, which influenced Griffin's views of art and the creative process. Griffin met Mollett at The Water Espresso Gallery Wednesday night open readings. In 1980 Mollett established ZtZu with artist Neal Taylor.
    - Moore, Shanna (Box 165, Folder 6)
      Poems by Moore and a letter from Tony Scibella.
      Shanna Baldwin-Moore is a Venice Beat poet and a collagist, one of the original Venice Beats. A Washington state native, in 1956 after graduating high school she migrated to Southern California where she lived and attended Pasadena City College. Eventually Baldwin-Moore moved to Venice where she met Venice West poet James Ryan Morris at the Carousel, a gay bar on the Venice Boardwalk where Jimmy scored drugs. In 1961 Baldwin-Moore relocated to Seattle with Morris, where she gave birth to their daughter Danette (Leos) Costello. According to Baldwin-Moore, Morris began public drug debates with Timothy Leary in Seattle. The debates ultimately took Morris to Denver around 1965 where he met Diana, whom he married. Soon after Morris settled in Denver, many of the Venice West poets followed him there, where the Venice West Beat scene continued to flourish. Morris died in Denver in 1978. In 1970, Baldwin-Moore moved to Hawaii, where, as of 2016, she still writes.
    - Moore, Todd (Box 165, Folder 7)